<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>programming on Daniel Martins</title><link>https://danielfm.me/tags/programming/</link><description>Recent content in programming on Daniel Martins</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://danielfm.me/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Functional Programming 101 - With Clojure</title><link>https://danielfm.me/post/functional-programming-101-with-clojure/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://danielfm.me/post/functional-programming-101-with-clojure/</guid><description>Here goes a simple yet interesting programming problem originally proposed by Mattox Beckman. After seeing Tejas Dinkar&amp;rsquo;s take on this problem using Haskell, I decided to give it a go with Clojure.
You are Hercules, about to fight the dreaded Hydra. The Hydra has 9 heads. When a head is chopped off, it spawns 8 more heads. When one of these 8 heads is cut off, each one spawns out 7 more heads.</description></item><item><title>Learning From Data - Course Review</title><link>https://danielfm.me/post/learning-from-data/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://danielfm.me/post/learning-from-data/</guid><description>Machine learning students and practitioners looking for a solid foundation on the subject probably heard about Learning From Data, a real Caltech course taught by Professor Yaser Abu-Mostafa and broadcast live, for free.
As a contribution to this wonderful initiative, I gather here my impressions regarding some aspects of the course.
Prerequisites Basic probability, matrices, and calculus. According to the course website, this is all you need to know. I would add programming to that list though, since it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to write some tricky programs in order to answer to some questions.</description></item></channel></rss>